<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Iesuites Pater noster giuen to Phillip III King of Spaine for his new yeares gift this present yeare. 1611. Together with the Ave Maria. Written first in French: Englished by W.I.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04412</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14534</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106453</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842169</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842169</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6801</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04412)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6801)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 743:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Iesuites Pater noster giuen to Phillip III King of Spaine for his new yeares gift this present yeare. 1611. Together with the Ave Maria. Written first in French: Englished by W.I.</title>
                  <author>W. I., fl. 1611.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ioseph Barnes [i.e. T. Dawson?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford [i.e. London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Suggested actual imprint information from STC.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>A bitter satire against the Jesuits--Madan.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6801:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6801:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE IESVITES PATER NOSTER Giuen TO PHILLIP III KING of SPAINE for his new yeares gift this preſent yeare. 1611.</p>
            <p>Together with the Ave Maria.</p>
            <p>Written firſt in French: Engli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by <hi>W. I.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at Oxford by <hi>Ioſeph Barnes.</hi> 1611.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="Pater Noster" type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:6801:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6801:2"/>
            <head>THE IESVITS PATER NOSTER.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>O Mighty Phillip King Of men</l>
               <l>we alwaies with a faithfull heart,</l>
               <l>Confeſſe we are thy children deare,</l>
               <l>And eke acknowledge that thou art,</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>Paternoſter</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All Ieſuits for thy worthy gifts</l>
               <l>Which vnto vs from thee did ſpring,</l>
               <l>Do ſing this ſong continually</l>
               <l>Bleſſed be thou O mighty King,</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>Qui es in coelis</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Rauilliack from a curſed race</l>
               <l>So well by vs inſtructed firſt,</l>
               <l>For maſſacring the King of France</l>
               <l>Inſteed of being ſtill accurſt,</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>Sancttificetur</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This blow great Phillip may declare,</l>
               <l>We are thy friends moſt conſtantly,</l>
               <l>And that throughout the world we'l ſpread,</l>
               <l>Maugre thy greateſt enemy.</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>Nomen tuum.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy moſt immoderate deſire,</l>
               <l>Of rule and gouernment to gaine</l>
               <l>And thy deſigne moſt wonderfull</l>
               <l>Ouer all other Kings to raigne</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>Adueniat.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some men whome enuy ouercomes</l>
               <l>Do much condemne thy greedy minde</l>
               <l>But by the right of thy deſert</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:6801:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>O puiſſant King of matchleſſe power,</l>
               <l>Whoſe name with reuerence we adore:</l>
               <l>What wilt thou haue? wiſh, and command</l>
               <l>Speake onely this, and ſay no more.</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>fiat.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And then ſtraight way, our holy troupe</l>
               <l>Shall ſtriue who ſhall be moſt free-wild</l>
               <l>To doe his beſt without conſtraint</l>
               <l>That through the world may be fulfild.</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>voluntas tua.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such great attempts to vndertake,</l>
               <l>The wrath of God thou needſt not feare</l>
               <l>For we haue power in our hands</l>
               <l>To make thee euen as happy here</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>ſicut in coelis.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We haue the gift of flatterie</l>
               <l>T'enchant thy foes, and vnder ſeete,</l>
               <l>To trample them, and neuer ceaſe</l>
               <l>Till each lie wrapped in a ſheet,</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>&amp; in terra.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For thee our Princes wee betray,</l>
               <l>And widdow Robbers are we all:</l>
               <l>We doe diſturbe our countryes peace</l>
               <l>And this is that which we doe call</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>panem noſtrum quotidianum.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thinke nothing hard which we propoſe,</l>
               <l>Many preuayles both day and night:</l>
               <l>If thou in all things wilt abound,</l>
               <l>And wrong done by vs gaine thee right</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>Da nobis.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:6801:3"/>
               <l>There are amongſt vs of all ſorts,</l>
               <l>That can by treaſons kings annoy,</l>
               <l>Whereby we gather all the wealth</l>
               <l>Which in our houſes we inioy.</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>Hodie.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If ſome ſay we are couetous,</l>
               <l>O King beleeue not what they ſay:</l>
               <l>But let thy Iuſtice then take place,</l>
               <l>And let them be condemn'd to dye.</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>&amp; demitte</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For they are ſoules of ſmall deuotion</l>
               <l>Which Sathan to himſelfe retaines,</l>
               <l>And for to iudge them Hogonotes</l>
               <l>The knowledge thereof appertaynes</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>Nobis</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe Polititians being beleeued,</l>
               <l>Alas! from vs all credit's gone:</l>
               <l>But ſure they all are Heretickes</l>
               <l>Which doe divulge to euery one</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>debita noſtra.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſuch as onely giue their mind</l>
               <l>To pray to God both night and day,</l>
               <l>And enimies are to Hypocrites</l>
               <l>They are not fit in Court to ſtay</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>ſicut &amp; nos.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With Kings and Ladies we frequent</l>
               <l>Being very watchfull of their ſtates,</l>
               <l>And of their goods, and of their ſoules:</l>
               <l>But as for poore and needy mates,</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>dimittimus.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:6801:4"/>
               <l>Phillip ſhew fauour vnto vs,</l>
               <l>We haue done many a wicked action:</l>
               <l>And ſure except thou ſuccour vs</l>
               <l>We neuer ſhall giue ſatisfaction</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>debitoribus noſtris.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If our deſigner deſcried be</l>
               <l>A due all plots whereon we muſe,</l>
               <l>To liue vpon neceſſity,</l>
               <l>Euen in ſuch ſort as good men vſe</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>et ne nos induca.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Th'occaſion now which France preſents</l>
               <l>(Within her kingdome King being dead)</l>
               <l>Of a young king and a Regent Queene,</l>
               <l>Hath cauſ'd our fathers to be lead</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>in tentationem.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Phillip thou knoweſt well that France,</l>
               <l>Doth wiſh vs euill for thy cauſe:</l>
               <l>Let not thy greatnes ſuffer her</l>
               <l>On vs to execute her Lawes,</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>ſed libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We neuer yet haue ſay led thee,</l>
               <l>Hold it as done, whatſoeuer we will,</l>
               <l>Thou oughts not to be ignorant,</l>
               <l>That all of vs are tempted ſtill</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>a malo</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>God make thee able O great Prince,</l>
               <l>(Following vowes Ieſuiticall)</l>
               <l>To make one prouince of the world,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd conſummate thy actions all,</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="Ave Maria" type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:6801:4"/>
            <head>THE AVE MARIA TO THE Queene of France.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHen Iudas with a kiſſe betraid his Lord,</l>
               <l>He ſaid, all haile: the Ieſuits will ariſe</l>
               <l>To kill thee (as thy King) a deed abhord)</l>
               <l>Speaking vnto thee in moſt humble wiſe</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>Ave Maria</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe baniſht perſons which through treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drew</l>
               <l>the dead kings tooth, with a moſt ſhameful doom</l>
               <l>Were puniſht: but at length was got anew</l>
               <l>(To draw his heart) a pardon ſent from Rome</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>Gratia plena.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Venice hath wiſely from her land expeld</l>
               <l>Traitors and Traitors wicked brood for a ye,</l>
               <l>Diſcords true Tender boxes which there dweld,</l>
               <l>Which you muſt alſo do that we may ſay,</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>Dominus tecum.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O bleſſed Queene if thou effect</l>
               <l>This deed which to thy ſubiects hearts giues eaſe,</l>
               <l>Confirming reſt whereof theres ſuch defect,</l>
               <l>Then ſhall be ſaid of her enioying peace,</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>Benedicta tu</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:6801:5"/>
               <l>They ſeeme moſt faire without, but are within</l>
               <l>Deuils incarnate, Hippocrites, Truthes foe:</l>
               <l>Their words are chaſt, their deeds are Sodoms ſin</l>
               <l>And doe amongſt themſelues as others doe</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>In mulieribus.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If France doe ſee (according to her vow)</l>
               <l>Her land of Treaſon plotters quite made free,</l>
               <l>Which good ſtates by falſe Doctrines ouerthrow</l>
               <l>With one conſent the Lord ſhall prayſed be,</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>Et benedictus.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe Ieſuits baniſht, truth reſtored is,</l>
               <l>Faithfull obeyſance thereby is procurde,</l>
               <l>Tis the repoſe, and Frances happy bliſſe,</l>
               <l>Tis the ſole meanes whereby may be ſecurde</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>Fructus ventris tui.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This deed achieud, you to your ſonne ſhall proue,</l>
               <l>A bleſſed mother: who to God ſhall pray</l>
               <l>That you with Chriſt may dwell in heauen aboue,</l>
               <l>And with good hearts true ſubiects all ſhall ſay,</l>
               <l xml:lang="lat" rend="rightJustify">
                  <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:6801:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
